Guide to the East Carbon High School Audio Visual Collection 1959-1980>
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
East Carbon High School audio visual collection
1959-1980
J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 801-581-8864 http://www.lib.utah.edu/collections/multimedia-archives/
A1045
East Carbon Museum
68 16mm film, 5 reel-to-reel audiotapes>
This collection houses a variety of cultural audio and video clips of East Carbon High School. Ranging from sporting events to school dances, the films and audio reels provide multiple first hand accounts of the high school from 1959 to 1980.
Historical Note
East Carbon High School was initially part of Dragerton before the incorporation of Dragerton and Columbia in 1973 that created East Carbon City. The high school, however, held the name from 1958 when the name and Viking mascot were appointed to the school. It remained one of the major high schools of Carbon County until 2005 when it was torn down and replaced by Bruin Point Elementary.
This collection has been digitized and is available on compact disc.
Ordered by chronology and format.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
Donated by East Carbon Museum in 2010.
Utah; Elementary and Secondary Education; Sports and Recreation; Student Life; Moving images; High school; Carbon County (Utah)
- East Carbon vs. Monticello 1959, 16mm film Color, no sound, grainy, 14:36 minutes (Reel 1)
  East Carbon plays football against Monticello.
- East Carbon vs. San Juan 1964, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 8:03 minutes (Reel 2)
  East Carbon plays basketball against San Juan at home. East Carbon wins 73-49. In the final shot, fans and players can be seen milling around the court.
- East Carbon vs. Green River 1965-1966, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 11:33 minutes (Reel 3)
  East Carbon plays basketball against Green River at Green River. East Carbon wins 57-71.
- East Carbon vs. Notre Dame 1965-1966, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 11:02 minutes (Reel 4)
  East Carbon plays basketball against Notre Dame at home. East Carbon wins 59-32.
- East Carbon vs. Green River 1966-1967, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 8 minutes (Reel 5)
  East Carbon plays basketball against Green River at Green River.
- East Carbon vs. Notre Dame 1966-1967, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 8:41 minutes (Reel 6)
  East Carbon plays basketball against Notre Dame at home. East Carbon wins 54-44.
- East Carbon vs. San Juan 1966-1967, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 8:50 minutes (Reel 7)
  East Carbon plays basketball against San Juan at home.
- East Carbon vs. Green River 1968, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 5:57 minutes, poor quality (Reel 8)
  East Carbon plays basketball against Green River at home. During the game, there is a small clip of East Carbon cheerleaders doing a routine. East Carbon won 77-52.
- East Carbon vs. Moab 1968, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 5:54 minutes, intermittent parts of poor quality (Reel 9)
  East Carbon plays basketball against Moab at home. East Carbon wins 63-55.
- East Carbon vs. Monticello 1968, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 8:48 minutes, film is washed out (Reel 10)
  East Carbon plays basketball against Monticello at home. East Carbon wins 61-59.
- East Carbon vs. Monticello, October 1969, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 10:56 minutes, intermittent parts of poor quality (Reel 11)
- East Carbon vs. Monticello (34-6), September 24, 1971, 1971 September 24; 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 11:02 minutes, intermittent parts of poor quality (Reel 12)
- East Carbon vs. Monticello (14-8) 1972, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 16:54 minutes, poor quality from beginning to 1:15 then improves (Reel 13)
- East Carbon vs. North Sevier (7-0) 08/31/1973, 1973 August 31; 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 16:55 minutes, grainy, low contrast (Reel 14)
  East Carbon plays football against North Sevier. It begins with a cheerleading routine until 3:23 and then the game plays for the rest of the film.
- East Carbon vs. San Juan (20-21) 1973, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 16:59 minutes, blurry, low contrast (Reel 15)
  East Carbon plays football against San Juan.
- East Carbon vs. Altamont (27-0), Homecoming, 1973, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 13:29 minutes, low contrast (Reel 16)
  East Carbon plays football against Altamont.
- East Carbon vs. Green River(28-8), undated; 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 16:57 minutes, low contrast, blurry (Reel 17)
  East Carbon plays football against Green River
- Moab vs Monticello (8-0), undated; 16mm film Color, no sound, 16:55 minutes, grainy, blurry (Reel 18)
  Moab plays football against Monticello. The video begins off with a different game, then switches to another game which is filmed in much better quality.
- East Carbon Basketball Game (75-28), undated; 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 8:50 minutes (Reel 19)
  East Carbon plays basketball at home. East Carbon is the team in white.
- East Carbon vs. Park City, Nov. 1961, November 1961; 16mm film Color, no sound, 16:17 minutes, grainy, blurry (Reel 20)
  East Carbon plays football against Park City at East Carbon High. Throughout film, there are shots of students and parents in the stands as well as cheerleaders on the side of the field. At the end, there is a shot of people rushing the field.
- East Carbon vs. Green River and Moab, undated1; 16mm film Black and white, no sound, recorded in reverse, 5:35 minutes (Reel 21)
  East Carbon plays basketball against Green River and Moab at East Carbon. This video is in reverse.
- East Carbon vs. San Juan, undated; 16mm film Black and white, no sound, washed out, 30:03 minutes (Reel 22)
  East Carbon plays basketball
- Basketball Leauge Games 1965, 16mm film Black and white, sound, 14:10 minutes (Reel 23)
  This is a video put on by the Small Business Adminstrations promoting print advertising for small business. It attempts to prove this through the help of a journalist seeking an interview with a new small business owner. Throughout the video, the journalist shows the price of no advertising as well as the increase of business with print advertising.
- East Carbon vs. Monticello, 1972, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 12:56 minutes, blurry (Reel 27)
  East Carbon plays football against Monticello at Monticello. East Carbon loses 12-0.
- East Carbon vs. San Juan, 1972, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 13:13 minutes, blurry (Reel 28)
  East Carbon plays football against San Juan at San Juan. East Carbon wins 12-7.
- East Carbon vs. Monticello (15-20), 1973, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 6:47 minutes, blurry (Reel 29)
  East Carbon plays football against Monticello. There is also a performance by East Carbon cheerleaders.
- East Carbon vs. South Summit (6-42), Quarter Final 1974, 16mm film Color, no sound, 13:30 minutes, fading (Reel 30)
  East Carbon plays football against South Summit. East Carbon players are in the light blue uniforms with red helmets. Midway through the game, it begins to snow. East Carbon loses 6-42 and the video ends with shots of the landscape and the clean up.
- East Carbon vs. Emory(25-7) 1974, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 13: 23 minutes, blurry (Reel 31)
  East Carbon plays Emory at East Carbon. The game continues well after it gets dark, effecting some of the film quality.
- East Carbon vs. Duschesne(47-0) 1974, 16mm film Black and white, no sound (Reel 32)
  East Carbon plays football against Duschesne possibly at East Carbon. The game is played at night under the lights.
- East Carbon vs. Provo (6-23) 1975, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 13:16 minutes, slightly blurry (Reel 33)
  East Carbon plays football against Provo at East Carbon.
- East Carbon vs. Monticello (15-20) 1973, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 13:33 minutes, blurry (Reel 34)
- East Carbon vs. Beaver(39-0) 1975, 16mm film Color, no sound, 6:34 minutes, color deterioration (Reel 35)
  East Carbon plays football against Beaver at Beaver(Wildcat Mascots). The quality of this video cuts in and out.
- East Carbon vs. Park City 09/12/1980, 1980 September 12; 16mm film Color, no sound, 13:10 minutes, blue toned (Reel 36)
  East Carbon plays football against Park City at East Carbon. There are shots of the scoreboard, but they are too washed out to see who won.
- East Carbon vs. GRO(12-0) 1975, 16mm film Black and white, no sound, 9:58 minutes, grainy, washed out (Reel 37)
  East Carbon plays football against GRO at East Carbon
- East Carbon vs. Morgan 1969, 16mm film Color, no sound, 16:51 minutes, grainy (Reel 38)
  East Carbon plays football against Morgan as titled; however, the game is played on Monticello High School's field. The game ends 34-6 Morgan.
- East Carbon vs. Beaver(0-39) 1975, 16mm film Color, no sound, 17:02 minutes (Reel 39)
  East Carbon plays football against Beaver at East Carbon. This is only the first half of the game as the cheerleaders perform their half time routine right before this video ends.
- East Carbon vs. Juab, 3rd Quarter, undated; 16mm film Color, no sound, 3:26 minutes (Reel 40)
  East Carbon plays football against Juab at Juab. This portion is only the first part of the third quarter ending with a score of 6-18, East Carbon.
- East Carbon vs. Juab, 3rd and 4th Quarter, undated; 16mm film Color, no sound, 3:32 minutes (Reel 41)
  East Carbon plays football against Juab at Juab. This portion is the second part of the 3rd quarter and the beginning of the 4th.
- East Carbon vs. Juab, 4th Quarter, undated; 16mm film Color, no sound, 3:27 minutes (Reel 42)
  East Carbon plays football against Juab at Juab. This is the final part of the 4th quarter ending with a score of 6-34, East Carbon.
- Snow Invitational Track, April 1970, Carl-Shot Put, 1970 April; 16mm film Color, no sound, 3:27 minutes (Reel 43)
  East Carbon competes at Snow College for the invitational. This a boys only track meet in which the film shows javelin and discus throwing, different types of track including sprints, hurdles, and relays, as well as the shot put and awards.
- Snow Invitational Track Meet, April 1970, Part II, 1970 April; 16mm film Color, no sound, 3:27 minutes (Reel 44)
  East Carbon competes at Snow College for the invitational. This shows different teams competeing at pole vaulting, shot put, multiple running races like hurdles and sprints, and also discus.
- East Carbon vs. unknown team #1, undated; 16mm film Color, no sound, 6:40 minutes, washed out (Reel 45)
  East Carbon plays football against an unknown team.
- East Carbon vs. unknown team #2, undated; 16mm film Color, no sound, 16:53, detriorated film in parts (Reel 46)
  East Carbon plays football against an unknown team at East Carbon. East Carbon wears the red helmets and blue jerseys.
- East Carbon vs. unknown team #3, undated; 16mm film Color, no sound, 3:30 minutes, cracking on film, poorer quality (Reel 47)
  East Carbon plays football against an unknown team. East Carbon wears the red helmets.
- East Carbon vs. unknown team #4, undated; 16mm film Color, no sound, 3:22 minutes, cracked film (Reel 48)
- Pictorial History 1961/1962, 16mm film Color, no sound, 38:08 minutes (Reel 49)
  - Students (Section 1)
    This section of the footage depicts students in a variety of academic situations. It begins with students walking into school followed by a female PE class. Then, students can be seen entering and dining in the lunchroom. The next scene is of students dressed in costume, posing in the front of the school. It cuts to students leaving school before cutting back to students dressed in costume again.
  - Classroom (Section 2)
    The first scene in this section is of boys working on leather projects. The camera man says something to the boys and they all look into the camera. The next scene depicts a student giving a presentation to a classroom. The next few scene show the library, various hallways, and classroom. It then cuts to the basketball team getting a pep talk and visitors sitting around the gym.
  - Cheerleading (Section 3)
    The girls begin by posing for the camera. Then, they go through two different routines: one without pom-poms, one with them.
  - Swimming/Diving (Section 4)
    The first shot is boys diving into a pool for a freestyle race. It cuts between a few different stroke races and then gives a wide shot of the pool and spectators. Some of the boys appear to be wearing Utah gear. Boys diving on the low diving board is shown next before it cuts back to swimming. After a few more shots of boys swimming, divers go off the high jump. There are a few serious dives that have been slowed down and then a few silly dives, where the athletes are playing.
  - Biology Lab (Section 5)
    Students sit in a classroom filled with different test tubes and colored liquids. Both male and female students are working with these objects. It cuts to different students milling around the school and then to a typing class. The next scene depicts students dissecting star fish.
  - School Dance (Section 6)
    Students and chaperones are shown sitting around tables, conversing. It cuts to dancing where the students have coupled up. There are multiple different dances shown before it cuts back to another lab scene where students are dissecting frogs.
  - Dance Performance (Section 7)
    It opens with female students dressed in 1920 flapper style dresses doing the Charleston. There are between 15 and 20 girls dancing in a line. The footage continues with other students singing and dancing, but the quality is very poor during these parts.
  - Party (Section 8)
    The final section of this reel shows female students preparing punch and cookies before it cuts to people drinking and conversing in the same room.
- Pictorial History 1962/1963, 16mm film Color, no sound, 50:26 minutes (Reel 50)
  - School (Section 1)
    Adults and student gather around outside and proceed to eat food from a cafeteria. The next scene is students, both male and female, walking into school. Students sit in classrooms, waiting for others to arrive on the first day of school. It cuts to students standing around outside while girls cheer, and then, a man gives a speech or announcement to the group.
  - Parade (Section 2)
    It begins with men in uniform carrying various flags. They are followed by a student band riding in a car, the high school royalty dressed in gowns, and a boy covered in gold paint, holding a globe and shield. As the parade continues, the cheerleaders and various other floats proceed by the camera man, including the small child dressed as a Viking, East Carbon High’s mascot.
  - Football (Section 3)
    Students play a football game, white and blue vs red and blue. The homecoming royalty are shown in their dresses and then the rest of the game is played.
  - Costumed Students (Section 4)
    Girls and boys stand outside the school in silly costumes. Many of the girls are covered in makeup, more ridiculous than accurate. After various students in costume are seen, it cuts to the students, still in costume, eating in the lunch room. Inside, the camera cuts to the lunch ladies and then back outside to students in costumes, this time with the boys dressed as girls running through the frame.
  - Cheerleaders (Section 5)
    This is a dance routine by cheerleaders in green skirts and white sweaters. The little Viking mascot also performs with them. Another set of cheerleaders in red and white and blue dresses join these girls. The basketball players proceed to run through clapping cheerleaders.
  - Dancing (Section 6)
    The sections begins with girls dressed in 1920s flapper girl dresses performing the can-can and the Charleston in line. The quality cuts out severely, but two children and a man dance. The film continues with other performances that are hard to decipher due to the quality. The cuts back to the flapper girls performing with varying film quality. The end of this section shows couples in their costumes standing around the gym, posing for the camera.
  - Flower Ladies (Section 7)
    The next scene is of women wearing flower corsages in the office. They pose for the camera and then go about their business. It cuts to girls playing jacks in the hallway, sitting around, talking. Next, students are playing games outside including hopscotch. Three girls stand around in front of the camera, laughing and giggling. It cuts back to the women in the office.
  - Cheerleaders (Section 8)
    This is another section with the cheerleaders performing their routine, most likely as practice because no one is around watching them.
  - Hanging Out (Section 9)
    The scene opens with guys and girls sitting against a brick wall, messing around and studying. It shows more people sitting in the school yard. The next part is the students dissecting frogs. It cuts to geometry class and then students walking into class.
  - Fashion Show (Section 10)
    This section depicts a student fashion show. Girls dressed in a variety of different outfits walk on the stage and proceed to walk off stage with the help of boys. There are multiple different types of outfits including day wear, night wear, and children’s clothing. It then cuts to students at a dance with couples dancing around the decorated room.
  - Track (Section 11)
    This section begins with boys running around the track doing relay races. It then shows medals being handed out.
  - Barbecue (Section 12)
    Girls and guys stand around the cafeteria and outside, grilling and dishing out different types of food. Students sit around chatting while they eat. It ends with a shot of boys standing outside a coal mine.
  - Canyons Trip (Section 13)
    The opening shots show students sitting on the bus. Then, there are shots of canyons and land formation as people hike around. Girls and guys play volleyball and throw water at each other. Some girls sit in bathing suits and others play in water. A couple of girls and guys get in a water fight, tossing water at each other and posing for the camera.
- Pictorial History-Part One 1963/1964, 16mm film Color, no sound, 19:32 minutes (Reel 51)
  - Outdoors (Section 1)
    Students play around outside, throwing water on each other. It cuts to students, dressed nicely inside the school. There are many people standing around, posing for the camera.
  - Graduation (Section 2)
    Girls and boys in cap and gown sing at graduation. People are standing around taking photos either before or after the ceremony. Students pose with their diplomas and stand around talking with parents and peers. There is one last shot of the class together.The last shot is of a blackboard with “May 8th 1964-grad day” written on it.
  - Play (Section 3)
    Girls stand around a microphone, singing and playing guitar. The play is Alice in Wonderland with the caterpillar, mad hatter, different suited cards, and the white rabbit. After the show, students stand around showing off their costumes. Flowers are passed around and someone makes announcements.
  - Fashion Show (Section 4)
    The fashion show begins with small children and their mothers showing off children's clothing. Then, the high school students begin showing off pajamas. The quality cuts out at this point. Another girl makes an announcement or a speech. There are a variety of different clothing styles like evening dresses and sport wear. The last shot is of women sitting around a table.
- Pictorial History-Part Two 1963/1964, 16mm film Color, no sound, 47:57 minutes (Reel 52)
  - Students (Section 1)
    Adults and students gather around outside an assembly hall. Others are seen inside, standing in the hall before entering another room. Many people are eating food and conversing in a large dining hall.
  - Bonfire (Section 2)
    Students stand around a large bonfire as some boys throw a straw man on top. The cheerleaders jump around, leading the crowd in a cheer. The scene cuts to entirely different unrelated content of women in an office, boys and girls listening to a record, a construction scene, and girls in pagentry attire, posing for photos.
  - Parade (Section 3)
    Pagent royalty sit in a car and then the band can be seen playing. They are followed by the cheerleaders and more floats with a variety of different themes. After the parade, the video cuts to the choir and then a big band on the gym stage.
  - Dancing (Section 4)
    Girls in flapper dresses stand in a line dancing the Charleston. There are a variety of people in 1920's attire. Two little girls and a gentleman dance on stage. Another girl sings at the piano. It appears to be some sort of talent show or performance as different people perform different routines from dancing and singing to acting out a scene.
  - Cheerleading (Section 5)
    This section jumps around to multiple different locations. Girls are cheering and then the boys are playing basketball before the film cuts to girls cheering again. It then shows girls in dresses with pagent ribbons before it cuts back to basketball and cheerleading. In one portion, boys have put on the cheer uniform and perform a parody of the cheerleaders routine, lightheartedly.
  - Dancing 2 (Section 6)
    The stage is set like a French Bistro as a girl dances the can-can before a boy in a white coat, black turtleneck, and beret performs a monologue. A boy band plays with strong Beatles influence. Others sit around on the stage watching the frivolity. There is some auctioning of art before a few girls perform ballet.
  - Gym (Section 7)
    In this section, both boys and girls are seen in gym clothes peforming calisthenics and stretches. The girls also do some form of gymnastics on mats while the boys do relay races.
  - Prom (Section 8)
    Students can be seen in fine dress in a room decorated like starry night. They can be seen dancing in front of a band while others converse at tables around the dance floor.
  - Track and Field (Section 9)
    This section shows a track and field meet. A variety of events like pole vaulting and long jump occur before some girls hand out ribbons.
- Pictorial History-Part One 1964/1965, 16mm film Color, no sound, 49:28 minutes (Reel 53)
  - Students (Section 1)
    It is the first day of school, August 31st, 1964. Students sit in classroom before it cuts to girls performing cheers outside the school. Boys stand around in leatherman jackets while a man talks to the group of students.
  - Bonfire (Section 2)
    Students stand around big bonfire.A small group of girls attempt to throw a dummy on it and miss entirely.
  - Football (Section 3)
    This is a daytime football game between East Carbon and Moab. There is some deterioration in the film quality. They stand around with gold football trophies after the game where East Carbon lost to Moab 7 to 14.
  - Mardi Gras Dance (Section 4)
    Large decorated letters spell out Mardi Gras. Students are in more casual dress as they gyrate all over the dance floor in 1960's style boogie. It cuts to girl students dressed in all sorts of different costumes.
  - Football 2 (Section 5)
    A football game between a white team and a green team. Cheerleaders can be seen performing as well.
  - Costumes and Dance (Section 6)
    Girls are dressed in a variety of stereotypical costumes like mammie, hillbillies, or cats. Girls sing while another accompanies them on the piano. Sashes are pinned on the pagent winner for the Sweetheart dance. There are girls dancing in the gym and couples sitting around as well.
  - Athletics (Section 7)